okay let's talk about HTML from a high
level perspective um HTML stands for the
hypertext markup language we talked
about hypertext before it's the
hypertext is the is the really ancient
idea of like taking text and clicking on
it having it linked to something else so
that's where HTML comes from the latest
living standard was updated on 31st of
May 2024 which would be today yesterday
and we're going to go to the we're going
to go the documentation the standard uh
specification did a separate video about
how to find that and why I use this
instead of everything else and we're
going to interpret this spec here okay
so the first thing is the HTML syntax
what is it about writing HTML documents
you can read all this on your own uh
writing an HTML document I might need to
zoom in on this actually do you guys
need me to zoom
in uh how about that a little bit better
um so uh this this again so HTML syntax
documents must consider see the
following parts uh a b order mark this
is a special ancient thing that you
don't need to worry about any number of
comments in whitespace whitespace is
just stuff you can't see that includes
uh spaces and tabs and thing a doc type
at which we'll talk about any number of
comments in whites space and document
element in the form of HTML and then
comments and then stuff inside of the
HTML which is part of the document okay
so what I want to talk about today
specifically though is the elements so
we've already we did another video
already about this um uh which is right
after this uh to talk about here this
breakdown so there's a doc type there's
the HTML and there's an attribute here
but let's talk about the actual little
they're called tokens these little
things here um so the start tags a start
tag start tags must have the following
format the first character must be a
less than sign sometimes called an angle
bracket uh this is the Unicode for that
and I mean at this point we're going to
go ahead and talk about what Unicode is
okay um so
Unicode uh what is
Unicode Unicode is the specification
that gave us emojis and all kinds of
cool things um I mean if you want to ask
Chad GPT we can do that what is
Unicode and Universal encoding standard
allows computers to represent and
manipulate character from nearly all
languages in the world uh including
Klingon by the way and unique numbers to
each
character yeah and it can be used to
display text on the screen it purpose is
to ensure that the digital devices can
display the same thing so the the idea
of Unicode is pretty simple Unicode just
says use the same sort of thing um uh
you know text uh to represent every
possible thing that could be
displayed um I do feel like we need a
separate video on that but that's going
to get us for enough for today um but
when we go back to the specification
standard this means it's a Unicode
character so that's what that's about
that's why I told you about that I will
make a separate video on Unicode and
we'll dive into it it's kind of cool uh
the next few characters are a start tag
it must be the elements tag name so so
we have this and then we have the tag
name we go back to our
example um in this case we have we have
there's one and then we have the tag
name H HML right immediately you can see
that this up here is something different
right there's an exclamation point there
that's because and I talked about this
other video this is an
stml uh this is technically not a part
of HTML it's a part of the HTML 5
standard but it says hey get ready an
HTML document is coming uh but there's
the tag that has been mentioned um and
then uh uh if there if there are to be
attributes in The Next Step they must be
first one or more asky wide spaces what
is an attribute so I'm deliberately
doing this am I not showing you the
screen sorry here we go let's do this
again so um the first character is a
start tag is a less than sign the next
few characters the star tag must be the
element's tag name now again people I
encourage you to make sure please use
the right terminology when you're
talking about this stuff it makes it so
much easier and I'm going to screw it up
and I'm going to work my best just use
the same terminology as well so what is
a tag for example people constantly call
um I mean a tag people will say yeah use
the HTML tag right what they actually
mean I'm almost positive is
element um they mean element and not tag
okay so what is an element an element is
the combination of potentially two tags
or it might be a void element where it
only has one tag so in this case the tag
uh begins and ends with a with a less
than sign here start tags must have the
following format they begin with less
than sign and they end with a greater
than sign and they have um they have a
tag name and then one or more attributes
as this is all this stuff says that it's
got here we go Lang equals whatever
right that is an attribute an attribute
is a key value pair separated by an
equal sign uh with I believe optional
whes space um let's see the tag name m
blah blah blah after the attrib or tag
name there are no attributes blah blah
blah and if it's a void element that
means uh then there may be a single
solidus character a slash uh on the
foreign elements that means it's
actually okay this is not valid but but
having a slash there for a void element
like a Break um is okay and it's a part
of the leftover standard um so having a
br slash like that that is okay see how
it's okay that's because it's it's a
void element that means it doesn't need
it uh in previous specifications you had
to do that but you no longer need to do
that as long as HTML 5 knows that it is
a void tag what is a void tag once again
a void tag is a tag that has no required
closer closing tag so as an element so
here we go so we got body that's the
start tag and we have slash body which
is the closing tag uh or n tag as I said
here let's use the right
terminology um and so so there you go uh
attributes attributes are key value
pairs that are separated by an equal
sign um and the they it's actually the
use of the uh quotes around uh the value
is actually optional but it's usually a
good practice to use that um uh may be
written in any mix of asy low or a
attribute values are a mixture of text
and character
references um attributes can be
specified in four ways so you can have
an attribute that's by itself right it
does not have a value um you can have an
unquoted attribute value which is like
this which we talked
about um or you can have it have uh
quoted and it can be single qued or
double quoted um if single quotes and
double quotes are effectively the same
last I Che
checked H unless I
remember um so so there you go um there
are a number of
predefined
um uh elements uh to do certain things
and there's also special attributes you
can read more in the specification about
that uh for our purposes though you know
that a document uh a web document is
composed of elements and those elements
can be either uh regular elements that
have start and end tags or they can be
void elements that just don't don't have
an end tag and have an optional slash at
the end uh and that is it that that that
and then each of these elements can have
one or more attributes which are key
value pairs separated by an equal sign
um that is it that is the structure of
all HTML documents in the world and they
all comply to that specification so um
that gives you hopefully a good sense of
what it's going to be like we're going
to drill down
into uh the different major elements
next